<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- 
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
	-->
<book>
  <bookinfo>
    <title>Hades</title>

    <subtitle>Domain class and DAO development framework</subtitle>

    <authorgroup>
      <author>
        <firstname>Oliver</firstname>

        <surname>Gierke</surname>

        <affiliation>
          <jobtitle>Software architect</jobtitle>

          <orgname>Synyx GmbH &amp; Co. KG</orgname>
        </affiliation>

        <email>gierke@synyx.de</email>

        <address>Karlstraße 68, 76137 Karsruhe, Germany</address>
      </author>
    </authorgroup>

    <releaseinfo>$Id$</releaseinfo>

    <pubdate>publication date</pubdate>

    <copyright>
      <year>2008</year>

      <holder>Synyx GmbH &amp; Co. KG</holder>
    </copyright>

    <revhistory>
      <revision>
        <date>29.04.2008</date>

        <author>
          <firstname>Oliver</firstname>

          <surname>Gierke</surname>
        </author>

        <revremark>Initial draft</revremark>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
  </bookinfo>

  <chapter>
    <title>Sample application</title>

    <section>
      <title>Introduction</title>

      <para>In order to introduce you to working with Hades we will develop a
      small sample application managing customers. As Hades is focussing on
      development of domain classes and persistence it will not be a full
      fledged application but rather concentrate on that particular part of an
      application built around the demo app.</para>

      <para>We will start by assuming that only want to have basic Hades
      support stepping forward using more sophisticated features of it.</para>

      <section>
        <title>JPA</title>

        <para>Hades is considered a DAO framework to work with JPA. Although
        the DAO abstraction could be to simple JDBC access, too, we focus on
        JPA in this release. This concludes in support for all major JPA
        persistence provders like Hibernate, OpenJPA and Toplink.</para>

        <note>
          <para>Although Toplink Essentials is the JPA reference
          implementation it does not implement all features specified and
          furthermore shows some bugs regarding cascading persistence. Thus we
          advice to choose some other library instead, e.g. Hibernate.</para>
        </note>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Configuration</title>

        <para>To get started with Hades you need to setup your application in
        the standard Spring manner. The following examples leverage XML
        configuration style of the container but you could easily use other
        approaches as well. We will separate configuration into two files.
        infrastructure.xml contains a the basic infrastructure setup descibed
        in the next chapter. This one will be used over the various
        sophistication levels of Hades. Beyond that we will create certain
        further config files that </para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Infrastructure </title>

      <simplesect>
        <title>DataSource</title>

        <para>As you might already know, Spring's data base access support is
        mainly centered around working with a
        <interfacename>DataSource</interfacename> implementation. Although you
        should rely on more sophisticated
        <interfacename>DataSource</interfacename> implementations like Commons
        DBCP, Spring comes with <classname>DriverManagerDataSource</classname>
        out of the box that should be satisfying for testing purposes.</para>

        <note>
          <para>Environment specific configuration that highly varies between
          deployments should not be hardcoded into a Spring configuration
          file. Preferably, use a
          <classname>PropertyPlaceholderConfigurer</classname><footnote>
              <para>For more information see <ulink
              url="http://static.springframework.org/spring/docs/2.5.x/reference/beans.html#beans-factory-placeholderconfigurer">Spring's
              reference documentation</ulink> on that topic</para>
            </footnote> to externalize those kinds of settings into an
          external properties file that can easily customized by application
          administrators.</para>
        </note>

        <para>So we setup an instance of it in typical Spring Dependency
        Injection manner.</para>

        <programlistingco>
          <areaspec>
            <area coords="2" id="data-source.driver-class-name" />

            <area coords="3" id="data-source.url" />

            <area coords="4" id="data-source.username" />

            <area coords="5" id="data-source.password" />
          </areaspec>

          <programlisting language="xml">&lt;bean id="dataSource" 
  class="org.springframework.jdbc.datasource.DriverManagerDataSource"&gt;
  &lt;property name="driverClassName" value="com.mysql.jdbc.Driver"/&gt;
  &lt;property name="url" value="jdbc:mysql://localhost:3306/hades" /&gt;
  &lt;property name="username" value="username" /&gt;
  &lt;property name="password" value="password" /&gt;
&lt;/bean&gt;</programlisting>

          <calloutlist>
            <callout arearefs="data-source.driver-class-name">
              <para>Configure your database vendor's specific driver
              class</para>
            </callout>

            <callout arearefs="data-source.url">
              <para>Point the data source to your database's location</para>
            </callout>

            <callout arearefs="data-source.username data-source.password">
              <para>Authentication credentials</para>
            </callout>
          </calloutlist>
        </programlistingco>
      </simplesect>

      <simplesect>
        <title>EntityManager(Factory)</title>

        <para></para>

        <programlistingco>
          <areaspec>
            <area coords="3" id="entity-manager-factory.data-source" />

            <area coords="4" id="entity-manager-factory.jpa-vendor-adapter" />
          </areaspec>

          <programlisting language="xml">&lt;bean id="entityManagerFactory"
  class="org.springframework.orm.jpa.LocalContainerEntityManagerFactoryBean"&gt;
  &lt;property name="dataSource" ref="dataSource" /&gt;
  &lt;property name="jpaVendorAdapter"&gt;
    &lt;bean class="org.springframework.orm.jpa.vendor.HibernateJpaVendorAdapter"&gt;
      &lt;property name="showSql" value="true" /&gt;
      &lt;property name="generateDdl" value="true" /&gt;
      &lt;property name="database" value="MYSQL" /&gt;
    &lt;/bean&gt;
  &lt;/property&gt;
&lt;/bean&gt;</programlisting>

          <calloutlist>
            <callout arearefs="entity-manager-factory.data-source">
              <para>Reference the DataSource declared before</para>
            </callout>

            <callout arearefs="entity-manager-factory.jpa-vendor-adapter">
              <para>Apply a vendor specific adapter to add further
              configuration. In this case we use Hibernate and tell it to use
              MySQL dialect for accessing the database, generate the required
              database tables as needed and log SQL queries fired to the
              database</para>
            </callout>
          </calloutlist>
        </programlistingco>
      </simplesect>

      <simplesect>
        <title>Transaction management</title>

        <para>Spring leverages consistent transaction abstraction through its
        <interfacename>PlatformTransactionManager</interfacename> interface
        and provides a <classname>JpaTransactionManager</classname>
        implementation out of the box.</para>

        <programlisting>&lt;bean id="transactionManager"
  class="org.springframework.orm.jpa.JpaTransactionManager"&gt;
  &lt;property name="entityManagerFactory" ref="entityManagerFactory" /&gt;
&lt;/bean&gt;</programlisting>
      </simplesect>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Basic entities and DAOs</title>

      <para>Working with Hades will offer support working with domain classes
      and DAOs for the domain classes. The Data Access Objects pattern is a
      well known and widely adopted pattern to implement persistent objects.
      Nevertheless implementing DAOs for domain classes ist often cumbersome
      and results in boilerplate code.</para>

      <para>Generic approaches to DAO implementation can head two different
      roads. One approach is to implement exactly one DAO instance that can
      handle all domain classes. This mostly concludes in passing the domain
      classes type into every method call and thus makes the interface rather
      technical and clutters it with unnatural parameters.</para>

      <section>
        <title>Entities</title>

        <para>First we have to look at the actual subjects to be persisted -
        domain classes or entities. We will use both terms interchangeably
        during the documentation as both are considered to have the same
        semantical meaning: abstracting business entities that are held
        persistent to some extend. Not all domain classes have to be peristed
        as entities but we will assume a business class to be persisted in our
        case.</para>

        <programlisting language="java">public interface Entity&lt;PK extends Serializable&gt; {

  public PK getId();

  public boolean isNew();

}</programlisting>

        <para>Entities have to be identifyable to be retrieved from the
        database. Thus your entities will have to provide an id or primary
        key. The id can be of any serializable type, beginning with rather
        simple types like Integer or Long up to complex multi column dedicated
        key classes.</para>

        <para>The <code>isNew()</code> method is used by the DAO framework to
        distinguish a lot of operations and thus abstracting e.g. an
        <code>INSERT</code> from an <code>UPDATE</code>.</para>

        <para>Implementing Entity will allow your domain class to be persisted
        by the default Hades generic DAO implementation and leaves any
        opportunity to implement certain class hierarchies to you. This
        freedom results in a few standard JPA configuration tasks you have to
        do manually. Hades provides more sophisticated base classes your
        entities can extend. This will couple your domain class code more
        tightly to Hades but frees you from implementing boilerplate JPA
        code.</para>

        <para>So let's apply this to our domain model:</para>

        <programlisting language="java">@Entity
public class Customer implements Entity&lt;Long&gt; {

  @Id
  @GeneratedValue
  private Long id;

  private String name;

  public Long getId() {
    this.id;
  }

  // further Getters and Setters omittted

  public boolean isNew() {
    return null == getId();
  }
}</programlisting>

        <para>To persist customers you need to declare an interface:</para>

        <programlisting language="java">public interface CustomerDao extends GenericDao&lt;Customer, Long&gt; {

}</programlisting>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>DAOs</title>

        <para></para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Configuration</title>

        <para></para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Easing configuration - Spring namespaces</title>

      <para></para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title></title>

      <para></para>
    </section>
  </chapter>
</book>